NDGrapher & Commandos Developing Toolkit - Source Code

F.R.C.


If you just want to compile this project, double click on Build.cmd. With Microsoft .Net Framework 2.0 runtime installed, you will find the binary files under ..\Bin\.
The difference between Build.cmd and BuildWithKey.cmd lies in whether there is a strong name signature. Since I will not publish my signature, anybody who runs BuildWithKey.cmd except me will receive some compiling errors.

If you want to localize the software, see Doc\Localization.en.txt.
If you want to know about the architecture of this project, see Doc\Architecture.zh.txt.


The software is freeware without charge. All source codes and binary codes are licensed under the BSD license, see License.en.txt.
All the documents are not under the same license. You can copy and distribute these documents without any modification. You can also refer and/or translate these documents. All other copyrights reserved.

The copyright of the tool write_bmsb shipped with the software is held by jinshengmao.
The copyright of the library zlib1.dll shipped with the software is held by Jean-loup Gailly and Mark Adler.
The copyright of the documents obj_format.en.txt and mtl.en.txt are held by Wavefront, Inc.
