NDGrapher&CommDevToolkit Solution Structure Description
F.R.C.


The design principle of the solution is to ensure the usability of normal functionality, with simple platform-based popups for most exceptions.

The solution support configuration file and globalization. Both are realized with INI, to make it simple to translate. There are related codes located in "Setting and Globalization" code blocks, which is hard to abstract and remains like that.

All file formats and reading-writing logics are located in "FileSystem".
With the exception of BsmbDecoderShell, as it could not.

All the GUI and GUI logics are located in their respective projects.
